write a program to find the closure of the attribute , candidate key , equivalence of the two functional dependencies and noraml form.


Schema : EMP(eid,ename,dept,age,salary,experience) //where EMP is the relation

Let the functional dependencies be as follows:

eid->ename
{age,experience}->salary
eid->{age,dept}
dept->experience

In above example, let us find the closure of the attribute eid, i.e, closure of {eid}

Since we are finding closure of eid. eid is an element of the closure set C+. Now we go step by step.



Step 1: Select each functional dependency and check whether the left side of functional dependency is a subset of closure. If yes, add the right side of that functional dependency to closure set. if not, check the next functional dependency

Step 2: Keep on checking the functional dependencies until there is no more functional dependencies with its left side as a subset of closure set C+.

What is a subset? 
A set M is said to be a subset of another set N only if all elements of set M is present in set N.
Set N can have more elements than M.


So, in our example, eid is an element of the closure set C+. So, initially, C+={eid}.
First functional dependency says eid functionally determines ename.
Its left side ( {eid}) is subset of C+. 
Therefore, its right side is added to C+. Now C+={eid,ename}. 
Second fd (functional dependency) says {age,experience}->salary.
Here left side ( {age,experience} ) is not a subset of C+. So we check the next fd.
Third fd says, eid->{age,dept}.
Here left side ( {eid} ) is subset of C+.
Therefore, its right side is added to C+.
Now, C becomes, C+={eid,ename,age,dept}.
Fourth fd says, dept->experience. 
Here left side ( {dept} ) is a subset of C+.
So we are adding its right side ( {experience} ) to Closure set. 
Now, C+={eid,ename,age,dept,experience}.
We are looking again for a functional dependency with its left side as a subset of closure set. 
Since the closure set C+ is getting changed in some steps, there is more possibility to find another functional dependency with it s left side as a subset of C+. 
Again we go through every functional dependency. 
Since sets do not allow duplication, we should do nothing if the right side of the a functional dependency whose left side is subset of C+, is already present in closure set C+.
Second fd has a left side that is subset of C+. {age,experience}->salary. Therefore salary is added to C+. 
Now, C+={eid,ename,age,dept,experience,salary}.
There isn't any more functional dependency whose left side is subset of C+ and give at least one new attribute to closure set. Therefore we stop now.
Now closure of set C is C+={eid,ename,age,dept,experience,salary}.



Algorithm to Find Candidate Key from Functional Dependencies
First of all, we will see the algorithm to find candidate keys from functional dependencies. The input is functional dependencies.

Algorithm:

1. Find the attributes that are neither on the left and right side

2. Find attributes that are only on the right side

3. Find attributes that are only on the left side

4. Combine the attributes on step 1 and 3

5. Test if the closures of attributes on step 4 constitutes all the attributes. If yes it is a candidate key.

6. If not, find the relation exteriors, that is the attributes not included in step 4 and step 2.

7. Now test the closures of attributes on step 4 + one attribute in step 6 one at a time. 
All those combinations are candidate keys if their closures constitute all the attributes. */


eqivalence of two functional dependency

Given a Relation with different FD sets for that relation, we have to find out whether one FD set is subset of other or both are equal.

How to find relationship between two FD sets?

Let FD1 and FD2 are two FD sets for a relation R.

If all FDs of FD1 can be derived from FDs present in FD2, we can say that FD2 ⊃ FD1.
If all FDs of FD2 can be derived from FDs present in FD1, we can say that FD1 ⊃ FD2.
If 1 and 2 both are true, FD1=FD2.
All these three cases can be shown using Venn diagram as:fd1



 

Q. Let us take an example to show the relationship between two FD sets. A relation R(A,B,C,D) having two FD sets FD1 = {A->B, B->C, AB->D} and FD2 = {A->B, B->C, A->C, A->D}

Step 1.  Checking whether all FDs of FD1 are present in FD2

A->B in set FD1 is present in set FD2.
B->C in set FD1 is also present in set FD2.
AB->D in present in set FD1 but not directly in FD2 but we will check whether we can derive it or not. For set FD2, (AB)+ = {A,B,C,D}. It means that AB can functionally determine A, B, C and D. So AB->D will also hold in set FD2.
As all FDs in set FD1 also hold in set FD2, FD2 ⊃ FD1 is true.

Step 2.  Checking whether all FDs of FD2 are present in FD1

A->B in set FD2 is present in set FD1.
B->C in set FD2 is also present in set FD1.
A->C is present in FD2 but not directly in FD1 but we will check whether we can derive it or not. For set FD1, (A)+ = {A,B,C,D}. It means that A can functionally determine A, B, C and D. SO A->C will also hold in set FD1.
A->D is present in FD2 but not directly in FD1 but we will check whether we can derive it or not. For set FD1, (A)+ = {A,B,C,D}. It means that A can functionally determine A, B, C and D. SO A->D will also hold in set FD1.
As all FDs in set FD2 also hold in set FD1, FD1 ⊃ FD2 is true.

Step 3. As FD2 ⊃ FD1 and FD1 ⊃ FD2 both are true FD2 =FD1 is true. These two FD sets are semantically equivalent.



cannonical cover

Finding Canonical Cover

Algorithm to compute canonical cover of set F:



 

repeat
    1. Use the union rule to replace any dependencies in 
       \alpha_{1}->beta_{1} and \alpha_{1}->beta_{2} with \alpha_{1}->beta_{1}\beta_{2}.
    2. Find a functional dependency \alpha->beta with an 
       extraneous attribute either in \alpha or in \beta.
    3. If an extraneous attribute is found, delete it from \alpha->beta.
       until F does not change
Example1:

Consider the following set F of functional dependencies:

F= {
A -> BC
B-> C
A-> B
AB-> C
}

Steps to find canonical cover:

There are two functional dependencies with the same set of attributes on the left:
A-> BC
A-> B
These two can be combined to get
A-> BC.

Now, the revised set F becomes:

F= {
A-> BC
B-> C
AB-> C
}

There is an extraneous attribute in AB \rightarrow C because even after removing AB \rightarrow C from the set F, we get the same closures. This is because B \rightarrow C is already a part of F.
Now, the revised set F becomes:

F= {
A-> BC
B-> C
}

C is an extraneous attribute in A \rightarrow BC, also A \rightarrow B is logically implied by A \rightarrow B and B \rightarrow C (by transitivity).
F= {
A-> B
B-> C
}

After this step, F does not change anymore. So,
Hence the required canonical cover is,
F_{c}= {
A-> B
B-> C
}
